Finding Aid for Willis C. Patterson papers, 1952-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Willis C. Patterson papers 1952-1999, 1967-1979
Patterson, Willis C.
7.5 linear feet
2009161 Aa 2
Willis C. Patterson, the first African-American professor at the University of Michigan's School of Music, was an active faculty member from 1968 to 1999. He was a professor of voice and associate dean for academic affairs. Patterson directed the Men's Glee Club from 1969 and 1975 and spent summers as a faculty member at the National Music Camp at Interlochen, Michigan. While maintaining an active concert career and fulfilling teaching duties, Patterson organized a Black American Music Symposium and compiled an anthology of "Art Songs by African American Composers." Patterson played an active role in securing funding and mentorship for minority and disadvantaged students both at Michigan and in the Ann Arbor community. The collection includes some biographical material, but focuses mainly on his professional and musical career. It includes correspondence, research, photos and clippings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was transferred from the Center for Afroamerican and African Studies in September 2008 (Donor No. 10110 ).
No additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open for use with the exception of some student records.
The Willis C. Patterson papers include restricted material in the following categories:
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 8
Willis C. Patterson was born in Ann Arbor on November 27, 1930, and graduated from Ann Arbor High School in 1949. After serving in the Air Force between 1949-1952 he earned bachelor and masters of music degrees from the University of Michigan in 1958 and 1959, respectively. In 1993, he earned his doctorate in higher education leadership from Wayne State University.
After teaching at Southern University (Louisiana) and Virginia State College, Patterson joined the faculty of the University of Michigan School of Music in 1968, becoming its first (and, for a time, only) African-American professor. He served as professor of voice and from 1979 to 1998, was associate dean for academic affairs. Between 1969 and 1975, Patterson was also the Professional Director of the Men's Glee Club. In summer months, Patterson was part of the faculty at the National Music Camp in Interlochen, Michigan. While at the University of Michigan, Patterson organized a Black American Music Symposium and compiled an "Anthology of Art Songs by African-American Composers" that is still widely used by musicians and students.
Patterson served as president of the National Association of Negro Musicians and as Executive Secretary of the National Black Music Caucus. He served as president of VIDEMUS, a nonprofit arts organization committed to producing concerts, programs, and recordings of the concert music of African-American, women and under- represented composers. He was the founder of the "Our Own Thing" chorale, an Ann Arbor choral organization, and provider of free music lessons for promising Ann Arbor youth for more than 30 years. He also served as leader of the African-American Endowment Fund. In his honor, the Friends of the Pioneer Choirs have annually endowed the Willis C. Patterson Award to outstanding African-American members of the school's choir since 2005. (http://pioneer2.aaps.k12.mi.us/choir/pattersonaward.html, accessed in October 2009) Patterson served as a minister of music for the Second Baptist Church and the First Methodist Church in Ann Arbor.
Patterson performed extensively in the U.S. and Europe and appeared as bass soloist with major American orchestras. He was a Fulbright Fellow studying in Germany and a winner of the Marian Anderson Award for young singers. Patterson appeared as King Balthazar on NBC-TV in its landmark production of Menotti's opera Amahl and the Night Visitors (1963), which aired for eight straight years on the network and was committed to vinyl. He also had professional roles in Gershwin's Porgy and Bess, Beethoven's Fidelio and Puccini's La Boheme. He was the conductor for a BBC-TV special and a Philips recording featuring Jessye Norman singing spirituals and again collaborated with Norman on Great Day in the Morning, a musical based on spirituals.
Patterson officially retired from active teaching in 1999 and was accorded emeritus status at the University of Michigan School of Music.
The Willis C. Patterson includes some biographical material, but focuses mainly on his professional and musical career. It includes correspondence, research, photos and clippings. The collection is organized into ten series: Biography; Correspondence; Programs, Performance Material and Reviews; Photographs; Scholarship; University of Michigan Administrative Records; Other Administrative Records; Black American Music Symposium; Clippings and Student Records. The Center for Afroamerican and African Studies transferred this collection to the Bentley Historical Library in 2008.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African Americans--Music--Congresses.; Black American Music Symposium (1985: University of Michigan); Musicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Patterson, Willis C.; Singers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Choral organizations.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Music.
- Biography
  The Biography series (0.1 linear feet) contains biographical sketches and Curriculum Vitae, his Air Force honorary discharge certificate, academic information such as faculty activity reports and a recording agreement, and Fulbright information and correspondence.
  - Documents (Box 1)
  - Academic Records (Box 1)
  - Fulbright Information (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (0.9 linear feet) is organized chronologically with a few topically organized folders. There is no item level-order within the folders. The bulk of the letters are from Patterson's time at Michigan between 1968 and 1999 and primarily document his official correspondence. Included are both original letters sent to Patterson and copies of Patterson's outgoing letters.
  - 1964-1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974 (Box 1)
  - 1975, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1976-1979 (Box 1)
  - 1980-1999 (Box 1)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha (Box 1)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha -- Sweetheart Song (with cassette recording) (Box 1)
  - Black Art Song Series (Box 1)
  - Visiting Artist Correspondence (Groups) (Box 1)
  - Visiting Artist Correspondence (Solo) (Box 1)
- Programs, Performance Materials and Reviews
  The Programs, Performance Material and Reviews series (0.75 linear feet) collects programs, posters, newspaper clippings and reviews for solo and ensemble performances. Concert settings include academic institutions, churches, concert halls and festivals and span solo voice recitals, opera and soloist performances with orchestras, choruses and small vocal ensembles and as a conductor for student and professional choruses. Included is a photocopy of a newspaper clipping on Patterson's high school performance of Pirates of Penzance.
  - Programs and Performance Material, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Repertory (Box 2)
  - Glee Club Tour Material (Box 2)
  - Glee Club European Tour and Rehearsal Notes (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (0.25 linear feet) includes mostly black and white professional shots of Patterson's concert and stage performances. There are also snapshots (color and black and white) of performances and more casual settings, including pictures of family and friends. There are a few publicity shots of other performers and a few negatives. Of special interest are stage shots of Patterson in the role of King Balthazar in folder No. 2. The series' original order has been largely maintained, though there does not seem to be any intellectual organization to the series. Also, few of the people in the photos are identified.
  - Photographs, 5 folders (Box 2)
- Scholarship
  The Scholarship series (0.25 linear feet) documents Patterson's scholarly work including six folders on the "Anthology of Art Songs By Black American Composers" that he compiled and published, and a meager amount of material from his professorial career. There are two folders of musical arrangements of popular songs and his own compositions that Patterson likely developed for the University of Michigan Glee Club and some brief notes on a history of Negro music. (More information on the Men's Glee Club can be found in the Men's Glee Club (University of Michigan) Records, 1886-1994.)
  - "Anthology of Art Songs By Black American Composers" (1977) (Box 3)
    - Composer Biography Information (Box 3)
    - Composer Permissions (Box 3)
    - Correspondence -- General (Box 3)
    - Correspondence -- Publishers and Composers (Box 3)
    - Research (Box 3)
    - Text Materials and Composer Information (Box 3)
  - Course Material (Box 3)
  - History of Negro Music -- Notes (Box 3)
  - Musical Arrangements, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Repertory and Research Lists (Box 3)
- University of Michigan Administrative Records
  The University of Michigan Administrative Records series (0.75 linear feet) documents Patterson's administrative duties while at the University of Michigan, including various committees and coalitions, and helping to plan concerts and search for new faculty. Patterson was active in a number of minority outreach and advocacy groups on campus including the Advisory Committee for Graduate Minority Affairs, the United Coalition Against Racism, and helping select the King/Chavez/Parks visiting professor. He also organized a popular Martin Luther King, Jr. Memorial Concert in 1988 with over 60 instrumentalists, 100 vocalists, and 2,000 in attendance. Document types include correspondence and memos, minutes and planning notes, and invoices and expenditures. This series is organized alphabetically by topic.
  - Advisory Committee for Graduate Minority Affairs 1979 (Box 3)
  - Conductor Search Committee 1975 (Box 3)
  - Executive Committee Material 1971-1973, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - King/Chavez/Parks Visiting Professors Program 1987-1989, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. Memorial Concert 1988 (Box 3)
  - Sabbatical Leave 1989 (Box 3)
  - Summer Research Opportunity Program (SROP) 1988 (Box 3)
  - United Coalition Against Racism 1987 (Box 3)
- Other Administrative Records
  The Other Administrative Records series (0.25 linear feet) contains records of Patterson's administrative duties outside of the university. He was a member of the American Academy of Teachers of Singing and saved copies of their guidelines and best practices. He was a faculty representative to the Committee on Institutional Cooperation Minorities Fellowship Program, which recorded data on minority student success in university settings. He also collected newsletters for the National Black Music Caucus. In 1969, Patterson organized "Our Own Thing," a volunteer program that gives free musical instruction to Ann Arbor area underprivileged youth between the ages of 10 and 18. Records for this program include member and instructor lists, correspondence and outreach materials, and planning documents.
  - American Academy of Teachers of Singing, Guidelines and Song Lists 1941-1970 (incomplete) (Box 3)
  - Committee on Institutional Cooperation (Box 3)
  - National Black Caucus of Music Educators (Box 3)
  - "Our Own Thing" (Box 4)
    - Fundraising Lists and Student Lists (Box 4)
    - Membership Lists (Box 4)
    - Outreach Letters and Correspondence 1968-1975 (Box 4)
    - Operations 1969 (Box 4)
    - Operations 1970 (Box 4)
    - Operations 1972 (Box 4)
    - Operations 1974 (Box 4)
    - Operations 1975 (Box 4)
    - Operations 1978, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Wimberly, Brenda Benefit Performance 1997 (Box 4)
- Black American Music Symposium 1983-1986
  The Black American Music Symposium series (2.75 linear feet) documents a national symposium held in Ann Arbor on August 9-15, 1985, at the time billed as the first of its kind nationally. The symposium involved many of the most important scholars and performers of black music in America, including Undine Moore, Hale Smith, Kermit Moore, Billy Taylor, Eva Jessye, among many others. As director of the symposium, Patterson had extensive planning and correspondence duties, which are documented in this series. Included are form letters and invitations, as well as personal requests for attendance and financial support, planning materials, staff lists, programs, posters, handouts and drafts of schedules and participants. This series also contains a considerable amount of funding and finance documentation, such as interactions with the Michigan Council for the Arts, the National Endowment for the Arts, the National Endowment for the Humanities, and grant requests to private corporations. Finally, there are biography files on each symposium participant, though many of the contributors with last names starting with letters D-Z are missing. A few of these files include correspondence to and from Patterson.
  - Administrative Records
    - General Correspondence
      - General Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Form Letters (Box 4)
      - Mailing Lists (Box 4)
      - No Response (Box 4)
    - Program and Schedule
      - Chamber Concert Series (Box 4)
      - Compositions (Box 4)
      - Conference Papers (Box 4)
      - Symposium Context (Box 4)
      - Program Draft Materials (Box 4)
      - Program, Poster and Handout (Box 4)
      - Symposium Schedule of Events (Box 4)
      - Tentative Schedule (Box 4)
    - Planning
      - College Music Society Annual Meeting 1986 (Box 4)
      - Notes (Box 4)
      - Planning Conference Staff List (Box 4)
      - Planning Meeting 1983 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Council for the Arts (Box 5)
      - Report (Box 5)
      - Guidelines (Box 5)
      - Correspondence (Box 5)
      - Application for Grant, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Proposal (Box 5)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities
      - NEH Award Notification (Box 5)
      - Reports (Box 5)
      - Correspondence (Box 5)
      - Application for Grant (Box 5)
      - Guidelines (Box 5)
      - Youth Grant Information (Box 5)
    - National Endowment for the Arts
      - NEA Award Notification (Box 5)
      - Gifts (Box 5)
      - Application (Box 5)
      - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Music Publisher Rentals
      - Carl Fisher (Box 5)
      - Theodore Presser (Box 5)
      - Margun Music Inc. (Box 5)
      - G. Schirmer Inc. (Box 5)
    - Finances
      - American Federation of Musicians Invoice and Correspondence (Box 5)
      - Cash Receipts and Tickets (Box 5)
      - Fee Structure for Credit (Box 5)
      - Film Funds Trust Funds Invoice and Correspondence (Box 5)
      - Orders and Bills (Box 5)
    - Request for Funding
      - President's Account (Box 5)
      - Ann Arbor Area Foundation (Box 5)
      - Atlantic Richfield (Box 5)
      - CBS Records (Box 5)
      - Coca Cola Company (Box 5)
      - General Motors Corporation (Box 5)
      - Ford Foundation (Box 5)
      - Motown-Berry Gordy Foundation (Box 5)
      - Symposium Planning Conference (Rackham Grant) (Box 5)
      - International Women's Decade (Rackham Grant) (Box 5)
      - Rackham Faculty Grant (Box 5)
      - Rockefeller Foundation (Box 5)
  - Participants (Box 6)
    - Adams, Leslie (Box 6)
    - Adkins, Aldrich (Box 6)
    - Allen, Betty (Box 6)
    - Allen, George (Box 6)
    - Anderson, T.J. (Box 6)
    - Anderson, Walter (Box 6)
    - Andrews, Dwight (Box 6)
    - Apple, Darwin (Box 6)
    - Bailey, Benjamin (Box 6)
    - Baker, David (Box 6)
    - Bland, Ed (Box 6)
    - Bates, Leon (Box 6)
    - Batiste, Alvin (Box 6)
    - Baraka, Imamu Amiri (Box 6)
    - Billups, Kenneth (Box 6)
    - Borroff, Edith (Box 6)
    - Boyer, Horace Clarence (Box 6)
    - Braithwaite, James Rolland (Box 6)
    - Bridge, Thomas (Box 6)
    - Brooks, Garnet (Box 6)
    - Brown, Charles S. (Box 6)
    - Brown, Maggie (Box 6)
    - Brown, Marcellus (Box 6)
    - Brown, Rae Linda (Box 6)
    - Brown, Wayne (Box 6)
    - Brown, William A. (Box 6)
    - Buckner, Reginald (Box 6)
    - Buffkins, Archie (Box 6)
    - Buggs, Claraitha (Box 6)
    - Burgess, Gary (Box 6)
    - Butcher, Vada (Box 6)
    - Caldwell, Hansonia (Box 6)
    - Capers, Valeria (Box 6)
    - Carter, Roland (Box 6)
    - Carter, Warrick (Box 6)
    - Carter, William (Box 6)
    - Dawson, William (Box 6)
    - Detroit Symphony Orchestra (Box 6)
    - Jessye, Eva (Box 6)
    - King, Betty Jackson (Box 6)
    - Moore, Undine (Box 6)
    - Primus, Pearl (Box 6)
    - Suthern, Orrin (Box 6)
    - Whalum, Wendell (Box 6)
    - White, Melissa (Box 6)
    - Whiteman, Clarence (Box 6)
    - Wade, Ray (Box 6)
- Clippings
  The Clippings series (0.5 linear feet) is a collection of newspaper and magazine clippings and press releases related to prominent artists, actors and musicians who apparently interested Patterson. These folders are organized by artist type and are alphabetically arranged, retaining the original order and categories. There is no primary source material in this series and little substantive information about the artists listed. Most folders have no more than one or two clippings.
  - Actors and Actresses (Box 7)
    - Al Fann Theatrical Company (Box 7)
    - Miller and Lyles (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Artists
    - Dempsey, Richard (Box 7)
    - Fax, Elton (Box 7)
    - White, Charles (Box 7)
  - Dancers and Dance Groups
    - Alvin Ailey Dance Group (Box 7)
    - Dance Theater of Harlem (Box 7)
    - Dunham, Katherine (Box 7)
    - Falana, Lola (Box 7)
    - Fort, Sylvia (Box 7)
    - Holder, Geoffrey (Box 7)
    - Malidor, Lisette (Box 7)
    - Mitchell, Arthur (Box 7)
  - Jazz Miscellaneous
    - Armstrong, Louis (Box 7)
    - Bailey, Pearl (Box 7)
    - Basie, Count (Box 7)
    - Cole, Nat King (Box 7)
    - Davis, Miles (Box 7)
    - Fields, Ernie (Box 7)
    - Gillespie, Dizzy (Box 7)
    - Hodges, Johnny (Box 7)
    - Horne, Lena (Box 7)
    - Lawrence, Morris (Box 7)
    - Mathis, Johnny (Box 7)
    - Mercer, Mabel (Box 7)
    - Quincy, Jones (Box 7)
    - Silver, Horace (Box 7)
    - Vaughan, Sarah (Box 7)
    - Williams, Clarence (Box 7)
    - Wooding, Sam (Box 7)
    - Loose Items (Box 7)
  - Night Club
    - Clark, Rogie (Box 7)
    - Collier, Terry (Box 7)
    - Havens, Richie (Box 7)
    - Makeba, Miriam (Box 7)
    - Reagon, Bernice (Box 7)
    - Davis, Sammy Jr. (Box 7)
    - Flowers, Phil (Box 7)
    - Jackson, Zaidee (Box 7)
    - Mannion, Elizabeth (Box 7)
    - Tyler, Willie (Box 7)
  - Performances (Musicals, operas)
    - Black Girl (Box 7)
    - Come Back Charleston Blue (Box 7)
    - Movies (Box 7)
    - Treemonisha (Box 7)
  - Soul, Rhythm and Blues
    - Anderson, Marian (Box 7)
    - Dyson, Ronnie (Box 7)
    - Green, Al (Box 7)
    - Jackson 5, The (Box 7)
    - Kendricks, Eddie (Box 7)
    - Little Anthony and the Imperials (Box 7)
    - Mills Brothers, The (Box 7)
    - Payne, Freda (Box 7)
    - Persuasions, The (Box 7)
    - Reeves, Martha (Box 7)
    - Ross, Diana (Box 7)
    - Sly and the Family Stone (Box 7)
    - Supremes (Box 7)
    - Temptations (Box 7)
    - Turner, Tina and Ike (Box 7)
    - Warwick, Dionne (Box 7)
    - Wonder, Stevie (Box 7)
- Student Records
  The Student Records series (1 linear foot) contains student applications to the University of Michigan Music Department, correspondence on degree requirements, financial aid requests, prospective student materials, academic recommendations, teaching assistant assignments, advising forms, and student coursework. Patterson played a large role in securing funding for minority and disadvantaged students. The correspondence in this series document these interactions between both students and the University administration. Because of the presence of student-identifiable information, access to the records in this series is restricted until 2055, in accordance with university policy.
  - Student Applications (Box 8)
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2055 ]
  - Degree Requirements (Box 8)
  - Financial Aid Requests (Box 8)
  - Prospective Student Materials (Box 8)
  - Recommendations (Box 8)
  - Teaching Assistant Assignments (Box 8)
  - Advising Forms (Box 8)
  - Student Work (Box 8)